It's 4 a.m., and the big test is in eight hours,
إنها الساعة الرابعة صباحًا، والاختبار الكبير بقيت له 8 ساعات،
followed by a piano recital.
متبوعًا بحفل بيانو.
You've been studying and playing for days, but you still don't feel ready for either.
لقد كنت تدرس وتعزف لأيام لكن لا زلت غير مستعد لأي منهم.
So, what can you do?
إذًا ماذا تفعل؟
Well, you can drink another cup of coffee
تقدر أن تشرب كوبًا آخر من القهوة
and spend the next few hours cramming and practicing,
وتمضي الساعات التالية تحفظ وتتمرن.
but believe it or not,
لكن صدق أم لا تصدق،
you might be better off closing the books, putting away the music,
قد تكون أفضل حالا إن أغلقت الكتب، وأوقفت الموسيقى،
and going to sleep.
ونمت.
Sleep occupies nearly a third of our lives,
النوم يستغرق نحو ثلث حياتنا،
but many of us give surprisingly little attention and care to it.
لكن الكثير منا يعيره اهتمامًا قليلًا جدًا.
This neglect is often the result of a major misunderstanding.
هذا الإهمال نتيجة لسوء فهم كبير.
Sleep isn't lost time,
النوم ليس وقتًا ضائعًا،
or just a way to rest when all our important work is done.
أو طريقة للراحة بعد انتهاء كل العمل الهام.
Instead, it's a critical function,
على العكس، إنه عملية أساسية،
during which your body balances and regulates its vital systems,
يوازن الجسم خلالها أجهزته الحيوية ويضبطها،
affecting respiration
مؤثرًا على التنفس
and regulating everything from circulation to growth and immune response.
وضابطًا كل شيء من الدورة الدموية للنمو لاستجابة المناعة.
That's great, but you can worry about all those things after this test, right?
رائع، لكن تستطيع أن تهتم بكل تلك الأمور بعد الاختبار، صحيح؟
Well, not so fast.
حسنًا، ليس كذلك.
It turns out that sleep is also crucial for your brain,
يظهر أن النوم جوهري لدماغك أيضًا،
with a fifth of your body's circulatory blood
حيث أن خمس دم جسمك
being channeled to it as you drift off.
يبث إليه حالما تغفو.
And what goes on in your brain while you sleep
وما يحصل في دماغك وأنت نائم
is an intensely active period of restructuring
هي فترة حادة النشاط من إعادة الهيكلة
that's crucial for how our memory works.
الضرورية لعمل الذاكرة.
At first glance,
من أول نظرة،
our ability to remember things doesn't seem very impressive at all.
قدرتنا على التذكر لا تبدو ملفتة أبدًا.
19th century psychologist Herman Ebbinghaus
عالم نفس من القرن التاسع عشر، هيرمن إبنگهاوس،
demonstrated that we normally forget 40% of new material
أثبت أننا في العادة ننسى 40٪ من المعلومات الجديدة
within the first twenty minutes,
في ال20 دقيقة الأولى،
a phenomenon known as the forgetting curve.
ظاهرة تسمى "منحنى النسيان".
But this loss can be prevented through memory consolidation,
لكن هذه الخسارة قد تُمنع عبر ترسيخ الذكريات،
the process by which information is moved
العملية التي من خلالها تنتقل المعلومات
from our fleeting short-term memory to our more durable long-term memory.
من الذاكرة قصيرة الأمد العابرة، للأثبت: الذاكرة طويلة الأمد.
This consolidation occurs with the help of a major part of the brain,
هذا الترسيخ يقع بمساعدة جزء هام من الدماغ،
known as the hippocampus.
المعروف بالحصين.
Its role in long-term memory formation
دوره في تكوين ذكريات طويلة الأمد
was demonstrated in the 1950s by Brenda Milner
أثبت في الخمسينات من قبل "برندا ملنر"
in her research with a patient known as H.M.
في بحثها مع مريض يعرف بـ"ه.م."
After having his hippocampus removed,
بعد إزالة حصينه،
H.M.'s ability to form new short-term memories was damaged,
تأذت قدرة ه.م. على تكوين ذكريات قصيرة الأمد.
but he was able to learn physical tasks through repetition.
لكنه استطاع تعلم المهام البدنية عبر التكرار.
Due to the removal of his hippocampus,
بسبب إزالة حصينه،
H.M.'s ability to form long-term memories was also damaged.
قدرة ه.م. على تكوين الذكريات طويلة الأمد تأذت أيضًا.
What this case revealed, among other things,
ما كشفته هذه الحالة، من بين أمور أخرى،
was that the hippocampus was specifically involved
هو أن الحصين معنيّ بالذات
in the consolidation of long-term declarative memory,
بترسيخ الذاكرة التصريحية طويلة الأمد،
such as the facts and concepts you need to remember for that test,
مثل الحقائق والمفاهيم التي تحتاج تذكرها للاختبار،
rather than procedural memory,
أكثر من الذاكرة الإجرائية،
such as the finger movements you need to master for that recital.
مثل حركات الأصابع التي يجب أن تتمكن منها من أجل ذلك الحفل.
Milner's findings, along with work by Eric Kandel in the 90's,
نتائج ملنر، بالإضافة لعمل لإريك كاندل في التسعينات،
have given us our current model of how this consolidation process works.
أعطتنا نموذجنا الحالي لكيفية حدوث عملية الترسيخ هذه.
Sensory data is initially transcribed
المعطيات الحسّية تدوّن بدء
and temporarily recorded in the neurons as short-term memory.
وتسجّل مؤقتًا في العصبونات كذكريات قصيرة الأمد.
From there, it travels to the hippocampus,
من هناك، تنتقل للحصين،
which strengthens and enhances the neurons in that cortical area.
الذي يقوي ويحسّن العصبونات في تلك المنطقة القشرية.
Thanks to the phenomenon of neuroplasticity,
بسبب هذه الظاهرة من المرونة العصبية،
new synaptic buds are formed, allowing new connections between neurons,
تتكوّن براعم شبكية جديدة، متيحةً وصلات جديدة بين العصبونات،
and strengthening the neural network
ومقوّية الشبكة العصبيّة،
where the information will be returned as long-term memory.
حيث ستعود المعلومات كذكريات طويلة الأمد.
So why do we remember some things and not others?
إذًا لماذا نتذكر بعض الأمور دون الأخرى؟
Well, there are a few ways to influence
حسنا، هناك عدة طرق للتأثير
the extent and effectiveness of memory retention.
على حجم وفعالية الاحتفاظ بالذكريات.
For example, memories that are formed in times of heightened feeling,
على سبيل المثال، الذكريات التي تتكون في أوقات المشاعر الشديدة،
or even stress,
أو حتى الضغط،
will be better recorded due to the hippocampus' link with emotion.
ستسجّل أفضل بسبب رابطة الحصين بالعواطف.
But one of the major factors contributing to memory consolidation is,
لكن أحد أهم العوامل المشاركة في ترسيخ الذكريات،
you guessed it,
كما توقعتم،
a good night's sleep.
هي نوم ليلي هنيء.
Sleep is composed of four stages,
يتكون النوم من أربعة مراحل،
the deepest of which are known as slow-wave sleep
أعمقها يعرف بنوم الموجة البطيئة
and rapid eye movement.
وحركة العين السريعة (ريم).
EEG machines monitoring people during these stages
أجهزة الرسم الكهربائي للدماغ التي ترصد الناس في هذه المراحل
have shown electrical impulses
أظهرت نبضات كهربائية
moving between the brainstem, hippocampus, thalamus, and cortex,
تتحرك بين جذع الدماغ والحصين والمهاد والقشرة،
which serve as relay stations of memory formation.
والتي تشتغل كمحطات نقل لتكوين الذكريات.
And the different stages of sleep have been shown to help consolidate
والمراحل المختلفة من النوم أثبت أنها تساعد على ترسيخ
different types of memories.
أنواع مختلفة من الذكريات.
During the non-REM slow-wave sleep,
خلال نوم الموجة البطيئة دون حركات العين السريعة،
declarative memory is encoded into a temporary store
الذاكرة التصريحية تشفّر في محل مؤقت
in the anterior part of the hippocampus.
في الجزء الأمامي من الحصين.
Through a continuing dialogue between the cortex and hippocampus,
عبر حوار مستمر بين الحصين والقشرة،
it is then repeatedly reactivated,
يعاد تشغيلها عدة مرات،
driving its gradual redistribution to long-term storage in the cortex.
دافعًا لإعادة توزيعها التدريجية للتخزين طويل الأمد في القشرة.
is associated with the consolidation of procedural memory.
يقترن بترسيخ الذكريات الإجرائية.
So based on the studies,
بناء على الدراسات،
going to sleep three hours after memorizing your formulas
النوم بعد ثلاث ساعات من حفظ معادلاتك
and one hour after practicing your scales would be the most ideal.
وبعد ساعة من التمرين على موسيقتك، سيكون الأكثر مثالية.
So hopefully you can see now that skimping on sleep
آمل أنكم ترون الآن أن إهمال النوم
not only harms your long-term health,
لا يضر صحتك على المدى الطويل وحسب،
but actually makes it less likely
ولكن يقلل كذلك احتمال
that you'll retain all that knowledge and practice from the previous night,
أن تحافظ على كل المعلومات والتمرينات من الليلة السابقة.
all of which just goes to affirm the wisdom of the phrase, "Sleep on it."
وهو ما تؤكده الحكمة القائلة، "نم على الفكرة."
When you think about all the internal restructuring
حين تفكر في كل إعادة الهيكلة
and forming of new connections that occurs while you slumber,
وتكوين الروابط الجديدة الذي يتم خلال رقادك،
you could even say that proper sleep
تستطيع حتى أن تقول أن النوم المناسب
will have you waking up every morning with a new and improved brain,
سيجعلك تصحى كل يوم بدماغ جديد ومحسّن،
ready to face the challenges ahead.
مستعد لمواجهة التحديات القادمة.